[Music]
foreign
automation tutorial
as you all know I've already published
12 YouTube videos covering different
concepts of tricentistoska latest
version 16.
so in my previous session I've covered
the action modes
select verify and then wait on okay so I
would recommend you guys to please go
through my previous session before watch
this session so that you can understand
the concepts very well and this is our
lesson 13 where I'm gonna teach you
the action mode buffer how can we use
the action mode buffer while automating
your test cases
and then how can you use the math
function while automating your test
cases so math functions and action mode
buffer are very very important Concepts
while performing some verification as
part of your test case automation
and also I'm gonna teach you Dynamic
expressions like Dynamic text
Dynamic numbers and the dynamic dates
how can you use Dynamic text how can you
use the dynamic numbers and the dynamic
dates while automating your test cases
and
provide your test data Dynamic test data
instead of static test data as an input
to your test case Okay so these are all
really very very important Concepts
to automate your test cases and to make
it very easy to automate your business
cases okay please do subscribe to the
channel
click on Bell icon you'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos
stay tuned and let's jump on to the next
slides
okay so what is our first agent item so
our first agenda item is action mode
buffer
so
to use action mode buffer while
automating the test so I'm gonna teach
you how to use action mode buffer while
automating your test cases
so any test case when you automate any
kind of test case it is very important
part of testing is to save and reuse the
values that the Sut has provided you
so this makes verification flexible
right so if you if you are able to save
some values retrieve from your system
under test or retrieve from your
application
and if you are able to save them in one
of the variables as a buffer so that you
can reuse them while verification part
instead of using any hard-coded data
save
generated values by using buffer
so this makes your verification very
flexible
what is the syntax you can see on screen
the syntax of buffer is open curly
braces
capital B
and your
uh and then Square braces open and your
buffer name correct and then close your
Square braces and then close your curly
braces so this is the syntax to use
buffer anyway I'm gonna show you
practically by using Tasker in next
slides okay
and then we should use this buffer only
be created and used in the same test
case so when you are creating buffer you
should be able to create in one of the
test case and you should be able to use
in the same test case you cannot use
buffer in different test cases so to use
shared test data you have a separate
concept called test data so you can
visit my long back videos related to
test design doc test design Tasker test
Design Concepts so you can visit those
particular videos in the playlist okay
and you can find the links in my
description okay so now
and what is our next agenda item let's
go to the next agenda item
okay so our next agenda item is dynamic
expressions
how can you use Dynamic Expressions
while automating your test cases by
using latest version of Tasker 16.
so I'm gonna teach you how to use
math functions and then how can you use
Dynamic text or how can you generate
Dynamic text and then use it as a test
data while automating your test cases
and how can you generate random or
dynamic random values while automating
your test cases and then how can you
generate Dynamic date while automating
your test cases so I'm going to teach
you with examples
while automating one of our test case
so now let's jump onto the system and
see how can we use all these Concepts
practically by using Tasker 16.
okay so this is my task
16. uh if you remember so in my previous
session we have covered action modes
right for that we have created this
folder and the entire test case
and I explained you about the action
modes verify select and wait on okay so
I'm going to copy the same folder here
copy
and let's duplicate the folder in the
parent fold parent folder okay
so I'm duplicating the work as of now
but going forward we are going to use
the reusable functions okay uh but yeah
for this session let me rename this
folder as
session 13
first let's let me cover buffer
and math function okay
okay so if you see e the agenda item
right if you see the agendas
first we need to cover the action mode
buffer and I'm gonna cover even math
function along with the buffer okay
so here
let's expand this
let's expand let's go to process
under process order product okay under
order product blue jeans when you are
actually ordering the blue jeans let's
go to apprehension choose
and go to Blue Jeans here we are
specifying the quantity
and the price I mean it shows the price
and where you are specifying the
quantity as 25 and AD code right so here
I want to capture the price of Blue
Jeans
so that
I can verify
the price of my blue jeans
during checkout process okay so now for
one blue jeans this is the price now
when I when I am checking out 25 blue
jeans right I want to verify the price
so that's why I'm gonna store the price
of blue jeans into a buffer okay
so if you see
this is my price container right I
already captured all the controls if you
see this is my price container and this
is my quantity edit box this is my add
to cart
button
right so for this price
I want to
capture the inner text
so if you go here simple see when you
want to capture the inner text go to
this Arrow mark
go to property
click on inner text
operator equal to
here specify the buffer variable name
price blue jeans price
blue jeans this is what the variable or
the buffer I want to store okay
and once you've done this see I specify
this here I need to use action mode as
buffer as soon as I select this this
equal will turn into Arrow mark that
means the inner text is
stored under the variable call or under
the buffer called price blue jeans
okay that's done now save this
and now one says to the price of this
blue jeans let's go to your shopping
cart
and let's check out these 25
blue jeans says continue continue
okay here before I confirm the order I
want to verify all these items whether
the price is correct or not I want to
verify the subtotal of subtotal
I want to verify if subtotal Plus
uh shipping ground these two hours
I want to verify subtotal and the total
along with the shipping shipping cost
okay
so
here
let's
go to for that let's go to one of the
folder called verification of prices
here in my previous session I have
already showed you
verifying the shipping cost whatever the
shipping cost is ten dollars right so I
would recommend you guys to
visit my previous session to see the
action modes verify
select
and then
weight on okay so we already verified
the
shipping ground cost as ten dollars so
now I want to verify the subtotal
go to subtotal what is my subtotal my
subtotal is now he here you need to use
the math function
what is my subtotal my subtotal is price
of each
one genes multiplied by the quantity of
the genes correct so that becomes my
subtotal okay so for that we need to use
the math function okay
math function curly blazes it starts
with curly braces so as soon as you I
enter math
it is showing me the math function okay
and then
open
braces
square bracket and again the buffer
function you need to specify under B I
already explained you in my previous
slides right
curly braces B
Square braces here you need to call the
buffer the where we store the price
right price blue jeans we already stored
so if you see it is automatically
populating my buffer variable that I
stored in my previous module correct so
call that
buffer
price blue jeans so let's price blue
jeans
and then
close Square braces and then you need to
close your
curly braces
multiplied by
Supply price of the blue jeans
multiplied by the quantity what is the
quantity that we are taking it's 25
quantity right and then make sure that
you close all the braces
okay
so if you see if the formula is correct
it automatically converts into math blue
genes which is sorry here
yeah math blue jeans
buffer multiplied by quantity which is
25 if you see he go back to by quantity
okay let me go back to start checkout
process if you see here
so okay order product okay if you see
here I'm actually adding quantity of 25
so that's the reason
I entered 25 okay so that is how you can
use math function and the buffer
function and also I want to verify this
subtotal okay what is the
uh
sorry what is my
subtotal correct so if you see here
my subtotal again the total sorry the
total if you see the total total is
the ground shipping method and your
subtotal correct so now let's go here
let's first store my subtotal what is my
stop total is this let me store the
subtotal into a buffer again okay
sub
total okay let me store sub total into a
buffer
here you need to store into buffer
okay
so here again the verification part I
have to convert into numeric okay I have
to make sure it's a numeric
so now what I am doing again subtotal I
am storing into buffer
and now what is my total
my total is my total ease again math
function
my total e is
subtotal plus my shipping cost correct
subtotal my plus shipping cost
so here again math function
math
okay math
open Square braces
open curly braces buffer
again open Square braces here I need to
call subtotal
right the buffer which I stored in the
above step
my subtotal
plus 10 correct subtotal close braces
Plus
my shipping cost here shipping cost
okay
close all the braces
so this is my
total I am verifying if the total is
equivalent to my subtotal plus shipping
cost of 10.
okay here I'm already storing subtotal
into a buffer okay so now let's run this
run this total test case okay let me log
out
and see if it works okay
close
let's go to shopping cart
right click
and run in scratchbook okay on
scratchbook so it's going to open the
webshop
click on login
it enters username password
appearance and shoes
and then you should click on Blue Jeans
now it enters correct and it's gonna
check out
done click on continue
so now at the confirmation page it
should basically
verify the prices if you see 25 25 plus
10 35 that's correct so successful the
execution should be successful
perfect I think a small there is a small
discrepancy let's see what is the
discrepancy okay so now if you see here
car total
card total
yeah this one totally failed because
okay basically what we did the expected
is 35 and actually is 35e
here
let's go back to verify prices
sorry verification of the prices
and here let me convert into numeric
okay that we missed so if you convert
into numeric it's gonna run successfully
and then
all the results will be passed
okay let me run one more time
it opens webshop
login
email address
a person shoes
blue jeans
enters the quantity
done I agree check out so now
the verification of two things one is
we are verifying shipping cost by using
verify
sorry ground shipping cost and then we
are using math function to add ground
versus subtotal right and then we are
verifying total amount
so now the result should be successful
perfect if you see everything is green
at the bottom so that means all the
results are success
see here let's go back to
verify prices
okay
verification of prices
method confirm order verify order
successful
let's see confirm order okay here
so here verification of prices if you
see
first one is we verified just shipping
cost is 10 10 by using verify function
and here we used
buffer method okay
subtotal is
the price of your blue jeans where we
added the price of blue jeans into a
buffer called price blue jeans and then
that multiplied by the quantity so now
that is equal to your subtotal that is
displaying on screen
and then we stored this subtotal
into a buffer and we are calculating
total by using again math function
subtotal
plus your
shipping cost right now successfully
expected is 35 actually is 35
okay hope
you understand our first two concepts
buffer and math function now let's see
Dynamic text and random values how can
we use these dynamic dynamic text and
random values okay and dynamic date okay
now for that let's copy this again let's
copy this session 13
copy this entire folder and paste it
into your parent folder
and modify the name let's modify the
name of this folder
as
session 13
here
dynamic
values and
Dynamic text
numbers
dates okay
done once you modify the name
now let's go to your
process and then checkout process under
checkout process I want to
go for a payment information
credit card okay here
so let's do one thing this time
I want to instead of using the card
holder name constant Barbara Gordon
instead of the static value I want to
generate a random text
okay a random text how can we Generate
random text that's what I'm gonna show
here okay
here
let's use the function called random
text
random text if you see here this is my
random text
my random text
and
what is
how much random text I want to use I
want to use the random text of 10th what
it means it actually generates a random
text
with the length of 10. random text with
the length of 10.
okay to validate these formulas right
earlier also I thought of let me explain
that see whatever the math functions you
wrote here
if you want to validate if the function
is correct or not right click and you
need to run
you need to translate the value
translate value
see if you see okay the value is
translated to 25 that means the formula
is correct
here again
translate value
35 that's correct in the same way here
random text you can basically
translate the value
see it generating the random text of 10
right
and then let's do random value so if you
see the credit card
whatever the credit card that we are
providing here
you can basically provide a random value
okay how let's say here the card code I
want to generate a random value
for that you can use RND okay Curly
braces R and D this is my function R and
D and
how I want
to generate the values from 100
to 999
so what it will do it generates a random
value between 100 and 999.
okay this is how you can generate the
random value
let's validate this
translate value
see it is generating 652 random value
and then
now
instead of let's use random dates okay
here instead of providing month
hard-coded value of April I want to
generate the date
how
let's create a date function
date
and here
I want to use a date function where the
date is
plus four months that means it's good
and generate a date
which is four months from now
okay it's going to generate a month
sorry it's going to generate a month
four months from from now okay what is
the format I want to print in the format
of mm and close braces
okay so here what it will do current
date
plus four months so that means and it
generates in the form of
zero four zero five zero six let's say
now it's a January that means it's gonna
go for
May
right
let's say it is February then it's gonna
go for March April May June okay so
basically I am actually
generating the date
dynamically I'm not hard coding the date
now
how can I generate year
instead of 2023 I want to generate the
year dynamically again the date function
date
this time
instead of month I need to use here
let's say I want to use the year three
years from now
okay
three years from now in the form of
YY
in the form of
okay
so let's close the braces
so if you see here what does this
function do
it takes the year
three years from now additional three
years from now in the form of YY okay so
now let's save all this and see how
these random all Dynamic values whatever
we provided here right Dynamic text
Dynamic random values Dynamic date okay
how does these translates into
application let's run this test okay
let's run this test right click
run in scratchbook
so now it opens
your webshop especially we need to
concentrate on your credit card
information that when when we are
entering okay is it going to generate
the random values successfully or not
okay
done
perfect
so if you see when it comes to payment
information now it creates
yeah if you see here now card holder
name is different
right you can see the card holder name
is different and everything is different
let's go and verify the results
okay
so if you see the results here if you
see the results here
under payment information
foreign
code and all these things
I think hope you all see
hope you all understand how to generate
the dates and all right random dates
Dynamic dates
Dynamic text dynamic
values
okay so this way instead of using your
hard-coded values you can generate some
Dynamic values okay hope you all
understand the concepts if you have any
queries
leave your queries in the comment box
I'll try to respond to your queries
thank you
hope you all understand the concepts of
how to use the action mode buffer
and then how can we use different kind
of dynamic Expressions while automating
your test cases by using price and
testoster 16. if you have any queries
you can leave your comments in the
comment box I'll try to respond to your
queries
please do subscribe to the channel click
on Bell icon you receive notifications
whenever I publish more videos thank you
[Music]
thank you